<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The orders lavves and ancient customes of swanns. Caused to be printed by Iohn Witherings Esquire, master and governour of the royall game of swans and signets, throughout England</title>
            <title>Laws, etc. Swans</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102212</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838009</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838009</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2366</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2366)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1055:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The orders lavves and ancient customes of swanns. Caused to be printed by Iohn Witherings Esquire, master and governour of the royall game of swans and signets, throughout England</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc. Swans</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Witherings, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 7, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by August. Mathewes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains 35 articles; another version of the collections at STC 9342.2 et seq.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swans --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Swans --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Game laws --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2366:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2366:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ORDERS LAVVES AND ANCIENT CVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOMES OF SWANNS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cauſed to be Printed by</hi> IONN WITHERINGS Eſquire, Maſter <hi>and</hi> Governour <hi>of the Royall game of</hi> Swans <hi>and</hi> Signets, <hi>throughout</hi> England.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of swan</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>London Printed by <hi>Auguſt. Mathewes.</hi> 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustrations_of_swan_marks">
            <pb facs="tcp:2366:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2366:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Kings Marke.</head>
                  <figDesc>swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Queenes Marke.</head>
                  <figDesc>swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Prince his Marke.</head>
                  <figDesc>swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Princes her marke</head>
                  <figDesc>swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Kings ſtay Swanns.</head>
                  <figDesc>swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Dutchy of Landcaſter.</head>
                  <figDesc>swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2366:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blank swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blank swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blank swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blank swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blank swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blank swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blank swan mark</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2366:3"/>
            <head>To the VVorſhipfull IOHN VVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERINGS <hi>Eſquire,</hi> chiefe <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Governour</hi> of the Royall game of <hi>Swanns</hi> and <hi>Signets,</hi> throughout the Kingdome of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our deputie Maſter <hi>Loggins,</hi> hearing that I had ſome ancient notes of the Cuſtomes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders concerning <hi>Swanns,</hi> deſired me that you might have a ſight of them, which I have ſent you; together with certaine Preſidents or formes of Commisſions for keeping <hi>Swanheards Courts,</hi> and Copies of ancient Patents, which I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of a very honeſt gentle-man Maſter <hi>Edward Clerke</hi> of Lincolnes Inne Eſquire, Father to Sir <hi>Edward Clerke</hi> one of the Maſters of the Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery. Theſe he delivered mee about 18. yeares agoe at what time Sir <hi>Lawrence Tanfeeld</hi> late Lord Chiefe Baron, and my ſelfe had a deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:2366:4"/>from Sir <hi>William Androwes,</hi> of that walke, which Maſter <hi>Loggins</hi> now hath from you. Maſter <hi>Clerke</hi> was before mee, but as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he told me he had his deputation from my Lord of Buckhurſt, and not from Sir <hi>Iames Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi> Howſoever, the titles are truely by mee tranſcribed, as I received them written with his owne hand. There are Orders alſo Printed; and yet ſomewhat differing from theſe, which Orders were made at one particular Court long agoe. And at a Court holden at Burford in the county of <hi>Oxon</hi> about 15. yeares agoe by the ſayd Sir <hi>Lawrence Tanfeeld</hi> and others, ſome new Orders were made; which Sir <hi>Laurence Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeld</hi> ſayd were Warrantable by the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and lawfull to be made, where and when they were fit and neceſſary for the preſervation of Swannes. Yet ſo that thoſe particular Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders may bee altered upon occaſion: But the ancient Cuſtomes contained under the name of Orders may not. There hath beene ſo little care taken for preſerving and publiſhing theſe ancient Cuſtomes, that they are not of all Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters knowne. And your deputies commonly ſend their ſervants among us, who as they are more or leſſe covetous, ſo do they impoſe more
<pb facs="tcp:2366:4"/>or leſſe upon us: And when wee that are the ancient gamſters oppoſe them, wee have ſome contention. You ſhall therefore <hi>(Sir)</hi> doe well, if comparing theſe with your other notes, you finde them to ſerve generally for England, as well as for our river of Thames: That you give to all your Deputies, and to all Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners copies, that ſo all gamſters may know the certaine Cuſtomes which are to bee kept: And ſo I bid you heartily Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Louing friend <hi>John D'oyly.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Alborne <hi>in Wiltſhire,</hi> 
                  <date>this 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>of</hi> Ianuary, 1631.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:2366:5"/>
            <p>THeſe Orders, according to <hi>Maſter Doyly</hi> his direction, I have examined and compared with ſome other Orders which are now in print; and have beene obſerved and uſed in ſome parts of this Kingdome: but I finde anciently uſed theſe Lawes Cuſtomes and Orders in moſt parts of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and not much differing from thoſe Orders now Printed, in matter of ſubſtance, but onely in forme. As alſo I finde a Commisſion uſed for the preſervation of the Royall game of <hi>Swanns</hi> and <hi>Signets</hi> directed to <hi>Noble-men, Knights,</hi> and <hi>Gentle-men,</hi> for the enquiring of abuſes committed contrary to theſe Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Orders and Cuſtomes, and the offences to puniſh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeverall qualities, and have cauſed theſe Orders to bee printed that thereby better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge may bee taken of them by every deputie Maſter of the Game.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOHN WITHERINGS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2366:5"/>
            <head>THE LAVVES ORDERS and cuſtomes for Swans, taken forth of a booke which the Lord of <hi>Buckhurſt</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to <hi>Edward Clerke</hi> of <hi>Lincolnes Inne</hi> Eſquier, to peruſe, <hi>An. Eliz.</hi> 26. On the backſide of which booke: It was thus intituled</head>
            <head type="sub">Taken out of an ancient booke remaining <hi>with Maſter</hi> Hambden, <hi>ſometimes Maſter of the Swannes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, If any perſon doth poſſeſſe any Game of Swannes, that may not diſpend fiue Marks a yeere of Freehold (except the ſonne of the King) the Swannes of euery ſuch perſon are forfeit to the King 22. <hi>Edward</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If any perſon poſſeſſe any Game of Swannes, and hath not payd his fine for the ſame: his Game of Swans is to be ſeazed for the King, till his fine be payd. Which fine is Sixe ſhillings eight pence, and no man is to pay it more then once during his life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But if any perſon hauing no Marke allowed him, haue one or more Swannes giuen him, or haue any Land-bird ſigne marked: he may keepe them in the common Riuer till the next Vpping time (without fine) paying the Commons and other charges for the Vpping.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If any Perſon hauing Swannes, either within <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2366:6"/>or without bee attainted, his Swannes are forfeit to the King onely, and not to any other perſon whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="5">5, Alſo all Swannes that are cleare of Bill, without marke or ſigne marke, are the Kings onely, whether they be pinioned or flying Swannes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Alſo all ſtray Swannes which no man can chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge by his Marke, thoſe are the Kings onely. And they are to be ſeazed for the King, and marked on the legge, but are not to be caryed away the firſty eare.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In all Common ſtreames and priuate waters when Cignets are taken vp, the owner of the Cob muſt chuſe the firſt Cignet, and the Pen the next, and ſo in order. But if there be three, then the owner of the Graſſe where they breed, muſt haue the third, for the ſpoyle of his Graſſe: and muſt pay to the King Twelue pence for the ſame Land-bird, ſauing in ſuch places where of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cuſtome they pay leſſe, or more.</p>
            <p n="8">8. If an Heiry be ledd with one Swanne onely, the halfe of thoſe Cignets ſhall be ſeazed for the King, till proofe bee made whoſe the Swanne was that is away; but are not to be caryed away that yeare.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Maſter of the Game, or his Deputy ſhall yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come at the vſuall dayes of marking Swannes in that ſtreame (on paine of looſing his Fees during his abſence) And he ſhall keepe a Roll or ſtandard booke, containing all the vſuall markes of that ſtreame. He ſhall alſo keepe a Regiſter booke of the number of euery mans Swannes, and the place where they are vpt. And ſhall likewiſe bring the booke of the laſt yeere. For which every Gamſter is to giue him yearely, Foure pence.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Alſo the Maſter of the Game, or his Deputy, is to haue a penny for vpping every white Swanne, and two pence for every Cignet, and ſhall haue his dinner and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2366:6"/>ſupper, and hay or graſſe for his Horſe diſcharged by the Gamſters every Vpping day, except in ſuch ſtreames where by ancient cuſtome other compoſition is vſed.</p>
            <p n="11">11. If any man deſire the Maſter of the Game to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any note in his booke (other then the notes due to be written as aforeſaid) or to take any note out of his booke vnder his hand, he is to pay for the ſame iiii. d.</p>
            <p n="12">12 If any marked Swanne be vnpinioned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by doe or may fly, the Owner of that Swanne is to pay Foure-pence. And if any man take any flying Swanne or Cignet, he muſt bring the ſame to the Maſter of the Game or his Deputy, and take for his paines 8. d. on paine of Fourtie ſhillings.</p>
            <p n="13">13 It is ordayned that no perſon ſhall lay lepes, ſet any Nettes, or Dragge within the Common ſtreames or Riuers vpon the day time from the Feaſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Croſſe vnto the Feaſt of <hi>Lamas,</hi> vpon paine ſo often as they be found ſo offending to forfeite 20. s.</p>
            <p n="14">14 If any Swanne be found double marked, imbeze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or by vnskilfulneſſe put out of right marke, the Maſter of the Game is to chuſe fiue Gamſters (ſuch as are indifferent) to iudge who hath right to that Swanne. And hee to whom the Swanne ſhall bee adiudged, ſhall pay Foure-pence for regiſtring the ſaid imbezeled or wrong marke. But if thoſe fiue, or the greater number of them doe no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> adiudge the ſaid Swanne to one of the Gamſters, then the Swanne is due to the King.</p>
            <p n="15">15 The vſuall dayes for vpping of Swannes are not to be altered without conſent of the greater number of Gamſters of that ſtreame, and that by Proclamation made in all market Townes neere the ſaid ſtreame.</p>
            <p n="16">16 No perſon ſhall goe on marking without the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the game, or his Deputy bee preſent vpon paine
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2366:7"/>to forfeit Fourtie-ſhillings. But if by ſickneſſe or other occaſion, hee be abſent at the vſuall Vpping dayes, the company may goe on, ſo that ſome ſworne Gamſter keepe the Regiſter booke, and receiue all the dues, and deliver them to him at his comming.</p>
            <p n="17">17 If any perſon doe imbezele, raze, or alter, the marke of any Swanne, to the loſſe or hindring of any mans game, he ſhall ſuffer one yeares impriſonment, and be fined Three pounds ſix ſhillings, eight pence, and for ever bee diſabled to be a Gamſter.</p>
            <p n="18">18 And to the end that in Vpping-time no Swanne be imbezeld, it is ordained, that no man draw blood of any ſwanne, till the Maſter of the Game, or his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty haue viewed the ſaid ſwanne, and declared whoſe the ſwanne is.</p>
            <p n="19">19 No ſwanne (other then Cleerebild) is to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for the King on the beake, but onely on the legge. For two markes on the beake are vnlawfull.</p>
            <p n="20">20 The Maſter of the Game may preſently ſell or cary away all ſwannes that are Cleerebild, imbezeled (as aforeſaid) and all ſwannes forfeit for want of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, or by attaint of the Owner.</p>
            <p n="21">21 And yet neither the Maſter of the Game, nor any other Gamſter may take away any ſwanne which is in broode with any other mans, or which is coupled, and hath a walke, without the others conſent, for breaking the broode.</p>
            <p n="22">22 It is ordained that Commons, that is to ſay, din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ſupper is to be paid daily by euery Banker or Commoner, whether he bee preſent or abſent. But if he be abſent, the Maſter of the Game is to lay it out for him (as likewiſe all other dues) till their next meeting or Vpping. But the ſaid Commons ſhall not exceed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2366:7"/>aboue Twelue-pence a man. And if the Company will ſpend more, they are to pay the overplus, by the Poll.</p>
            <p n="23">23 To the end that diet may bee had at a reaſonable rate, and likewiſe lodging: the place of taking both, is to be choſen by the greater number of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moners.</p>
            <p n="24">24 If any perſon bee found carying a Swan-hooke within fourtie lugg of any ſtreame, ſauing on the Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping dayes, and not accompanied with two ſwan-herdes, he ſhall forfeit Thirteene-ſhillings foure pence. But vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Vpping dayes, every Gamſter that caryeth not a Hooke (except ſuch Gentlemen as for pleaſure goe to ſee their owne game) ſhall forfeit eight pence a day, the one halfe to bee for the Maſter of the Game, the other halfe for the company.</p>
            <p n="25">25 No perſon ſhall take vp any Swanne or Cignet marked or vnmarked, vnleſſe it be done in the preſence of two other ſwan-herdes, and that by allowance of the Maſter of the Game, or his Deputy, for which allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance hee is to pay Foure-pence vpon paine to forfeite Fourtie ſhillings.</p>
            <p n="26">26 If any ſwan-herdes depart before hee haue made even with the Maſter of the Game, for all dues, hee is to forfeite Twelue pence: For which, as for all dues, the Maſter of the Game, or his Deputy, may diſtreine the game: and at the next Vpping may pay himſelfe by diſtraining and ſale of the Game, rendring to the party the overplus.</p>
            <p n="27">27 If there bee any perſon or perſons, that hath Swannes, that doe heirie vpon any of their Rivers, or ſeverall waters; and afterward come to the common water or River, they ſhall pay a Land-bird to the King, and be obedient to all Swan-lawes: For diuers ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do vſe colluſion to defraude the King of his Right.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2366:8"/>
            <p n="28">28 If any perſon ſhall take away the egge or egges of any ſwanne: Every ſuch Offender ſhall be impriſoned a yeere and a day; and ſhall pay Thirteene ſhillings Foure pence for every Egge ſo taken away. Whereof halfe to the King, and halfe to the Owner of the ſwan. 11. <hi>of Henry</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="29">29 If any perſon doe driue away any Swanne bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or providing to breede, be it on his owne ground, or on any other mans: he ſhall be fined 13. s. 4 d. and ſhall ſuffer one yeares impriſonment. 11. <hi>of Henry</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="30">30 If any Dogge ſhall driue any Swanne away from her neſt; the Owner of ſuch Dogge ſhall forfeite Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene ſhillings foure pence. But if any Dogge ſhall kill any old Swanne; the Owner of ſuch Dogge ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite to the King Fouretie ſhillings. Whether he be there or not.</p>
            <p n="31">31 If any perſon ſhall hunt any Ducks, or any other chaſe in the water with any Dogge or Dogges in fence time; (that is, from the feaſt of <hi>Easter</hi> till <hi>Lammas</hi> Eue) he ſhall pay for every offence, ſixe ſhillings eight pence.</p>
            <p n="32">32 It is ordained that if any perſon doth ſet any Snares or any manner of Nets, Lime, or Engines, to take Bittorns or Swannes, from the Feaſt of <hi>Easter,</hi> to the Sunday after <hi>Lammas</hi> day: Hee or they to forfeite to the Kings Maieſtie for every time ſo ſetting, 6. s. 8. d.</p>
            <p n="33">33 If there bee any weares vpon the Rivers, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grates before them, whereby the Swannes and Cig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets may be defended from drowning: the Owner of ſuch Weare ſhall forfeite to the King thirteene ſhillings foure pence.</p>
            <p n="34">34 All Fiſher-men are to aſſiſt the Maſter of the Game or his Deputy, in the execution of their office on the Vpping dayes, with their boates at the vpper end
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2366:8"/>of their ſeverall waters, vpon paine of tenne ſhillings for every default. For which ſervice the Maſter of the Game ſhall cauſe the accuſtomed Fees to be payd to the ſaid Fiſher-men.</p>
            <p n="35">35 Laſtly, If there be any other Miſdemeanour, or Offence committed, or done by anie Owner of any Game, Swan-heard, or other perſon whatſoever, contrary to any Lawe, ancient Cuſtome, or uſage heretofore uſed and allowed, and not before herein particularly mentioned or expreſſed, you ſhall preſent the ſame Offence, that reformation may be had, and the Offendors puniſhed, according to the quantity and quality of the ſeverall Offences,</p>
            <p>AT every Swan-heards court, all Offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by breach of theſe orders, are to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of.</p>
            <p>Note that the Swan-heard for the Dutchy of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter</hi> is to obſerve, and ſee obſerved, all theſe orders in his circuite, and to receive the Fees belonging to the Kings Swan heard.</p>
            <p>Note, that in all for feitures to the King, a fourth part is due to him that gives information of the offence.</p>
            <p>Note that none is to go as a Swan-vpper, but thoſe who are ſworne, if Courts be often kept.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
